<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynneth a goodly treatyse, and it is called a notable lesson, otherwyse it is called the golden pystle</title>
            <title>Epistola de perfectione vitae. English</title>
            <author>Bernard, of Clairvaux, Saint, 1090 or 91-1153.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1531</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1914</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108417</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844076</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844076</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8861</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08854)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8861)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 19:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynneth a goodly treatyse, and it is called a notable lesson, otherwyse it is called the golden pystle</title>
                  <title>Epistola de perfectione vitae. English</title>
                  <author>Bernard, of Clairvaux, Saint, 1090 or 91-1153.</author>
                  <author>Whitford, Richard, fl. 1495-1555?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by me Robert wyre, dwellynge at the sygne of seynt Iohan eua[n]gelyst, in seynt Martyns parysshe in the felde besyde Charynge crosse in the bysshop of Norwytche rentys],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Imprynted in the yere of our lorde god. M.CCCCC.xxxi. [1531]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An English adaptation, by Richard Whitford, of: Saint Bernard.  Epistola de perfectione vitae.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Perfection --  Religious aspects --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:8861:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8861:1"/>
            <p>Here begynneth a goodly treatyſe / and it is called a notable leſſon / otherwyſe it is called the golden pyſtle. Imprynted in the yere of our lorde god .M. CCCCC. xxxi.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>altered printer's device of Robert Wyer (1529-60) with his name, the eagle, and part of the foreground cut away, perhaps to represent St. Bernard, the supposed author of the Golden Pistle, composing that letter (instead of St. John writing the Book of Revelation on Patmos)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:8861:2"/>
            <head>¶ The Prologue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Good / hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome leſſon and profyta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto all chryſtianes / aſcrybed vnto ſeynt Bernarde / and put amonge his warkes (I thynke) by ſome good man that wolde it ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de thereby haue the more authorite / and the rather be redde and better be borne away. For doubtles it is a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de mater: &amp; edificatyue vnto all them that haue a zele / and cure vnto ſoule helthe and deſyre of ſaluacyon. It is called in the tytle. Notabile docume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum: that is to ſay / a notable leſſon. And ſome do call it the golden pyſtle It foloweth immediatly after a lytel werke called Formula honeſte vite. The forme and maner of an honeſt lyfe / or of honeſt lyuynge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:8861:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>f you intende to pleaſe god / &amp; wolde obteyne grace to fulfyll the ſame / two thynges ben vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you very neceſſarye. The fyrſte. You muſt withdrawe your mynde from all wordly and tranſytory thynges / in ſuche maner / as though you cared not whether any ſuch thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were in this worlde or no. The ſeconde is that you gyue and apply your ſelfe ſo wholy to god / and haue your ſelfe in ſuche a wayte / that you neuer do / ſaye / nethynke / that you knowe ſuppoſe / or byleue ſhuld offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de or dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe god / for by this meane / you may ſoneſt and moſt redely obtayne / and wynne his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour &amp; grace. In all thynges eſteme and acou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t your ſelfe moſt vyle / and moſt ſymple / &amp; as very nought in reſpecte / and regarde of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and thynke / ſuppoſe / and byleue that all perſons ben good / and better than you be / for ſo ſhall you moche pleaſe our lorde. What ſo euer youſe / or ſeme to pceyue / in any perſon / or yet here of any chriſtyane / take you none oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſyon therin / but rather aſcrybe / and applye you all vnto the beſt / and thynke or ſuppoſe / all is done or ſayde for a good intent / or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe / though it ſeme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. For mannes ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pycyons and lyght iudgemetes ben ſoone / &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:8861:3"/>lyghtly deceyued / or begyled. Dyſpleaſe no perſon wyllyngly. He euer ſpeke euyl of any perſon / though it were neuer ſo true that you ſay. For it is not lawfull to ſhe we in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vyce / or defaute of any perſon / excepte ye myght other wyſe ſhe we &amp; declare your owne offence. Speke lytel or nought vnto your pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pre / and ſelfe laude / or prayſe though it were true / &amp; vnto your famylyer felowe / or fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full frende. But ſtudy to kepe ſecrete / and pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney your vertue / rather than your vyce. Yet were it a cruel dede for any perſons to defame them ſelf. Be more gladde to gyue your eare / &amp; herynge vnto the prayſe / rather than vnto the dyſprayſe of any pſon. And euer beware as well of herynge / as ſpekynge of detraccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And whan you ſpeke take good delyberacto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; haue fewe words / and ſet thoſe be true and good? ſadly ſet &amp; wyſely ordred. Yf any wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des be ſpoken vnto you of vyce / or vanyte (as ſoone as you maye) breke of and leue that talke / or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munycacyon. And euer returne / &amp; applye your ſelfe vnto ſome appoynted good and godly occupacyon / bodely or ghoſtly. Yf any ſodayne chaunce fal or happe vnto you / or vnto any of youres / leyne not to lyghtly there vnto / ne care moche therfore. Yf it be of proſperyte / reioyce not moche there in / ne be
<pb facs="tcp:8861:3"/>ouer gladde therof. Yf it be aduerſyte / be not ouercaſt / or ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therwith / ne brought to ſorowe / or ſadnes / thanke god of all / and ſet lytell therby. Repute all thynges tranſyto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye: as of lytell pryce or valure. Gyue euer mooſt thought and care vnto thoſe thynges / that may profyte and promote the ſoule. Fle / and auoyde the perſones and places of moche ſpeche: for better is to kepe ſylence than to ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. Kepe the tymes and places of ſcylence pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſely / ſo that you ſpeke not without reſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vnfeyned cauſe. The tymes of ſcyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in religyon ben theſe. From collacion vnto maſſe be ended after the houre of terce. From the fyrſte grace in the fraytour / vnto the ende of the latter grace. And from the begynnynge of euen ſonge / vnto grace be ended after ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per / or elles Bn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicite / after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune beuer. The places of ſylence ben the churche and the clouſtre / the fraytour and the dortour. Yf you be ſclaundred / and do take occaſyon at that faute / or offence of any perſon / than loke wel vpon your ſelfe / whether you be in the ſame defaute ſomtyme your ſelfe / and than haue compaſſyon vpon your brother / or ſyſter. Yf there be none ſuche defaute in you / thynke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely and byleue there may be / and than do as (in lyke) you wolde be done vnto. And thus
<pb facs="tcp:8861:4"/>as in a glas / ye may ſe and beholde your ſelfe. Grudge not ne complayne vpon any perſon for any maner cauſe / excepte you ſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue by large co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture that you may profyte and edyfye therby. Nother denye nor affyrme your mynde or opynyon ſtyfly or extremely / but that youre affyrmacyon / denegacyon / or doubte / be euer powderyd with ſalt / that is to ſay / wyſdome / dyſcrecyon / and pacyence. Dſe not in any wyſe to mocke / checke or ſcorne / ne yet to laughe or ſmyle but ryght ſeldom. And that alway to ſhe we reuerence or louyng ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner / lyght countenaunce / or loude behauyour beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth nat a ſad perſon. Let your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacyon be ſhorte and with fewe perſones / al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> of vertue / lernyng or good and chryſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne edyſycacion / and euer with ſuche warenes that no perſon in thyngs doubtfull may take any authoryte of your wordes / or ſentence.</p>
            <p>Let all your paſtyme be ſpended in bodely la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures good and profytable / or ellyes godly in ſtudy / or that paſſeth all / in holy and deuoute prayer. So that the herte and mynde be occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d with the ſame you ſpeke. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you p<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ye for any certayne perſons / reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre theyr de<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire / ſtate and condycyon. For a forme and o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dre of your prayer / this may be a good and redy way. To folowe the ordre of the .vi. gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>matycall
<pb facs="tcp:8861:4"/>caſes. The nominatyue / the genity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue / the datyue / the accuſatyue / the vocatyue / &amp; ablatyue. The nominatyue / that is fyrſt to pray foryour ſelfe that you may haue ghoſtly ſtrength &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy / that you not fall in to any deedly offence by fraylte. And the .ii. that you maye haue ryght knowlege of god by faythe and of your ſelfe / by due conſyderacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your aſtate / and condycyon / and of the lawes of god / for your conyte and contynuatice. And thyrdely that you maye haue grace and good wyll accordyng vnto the ſame ſtrength / and knowlege / and that hauynge vnto god a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de drede you neuer offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de hym in thought worde / nor dede: but that you maye euer loue hym for hym ſelfe and all his creatures in oue ordre for hym and in hym. The ſeconde is the genytyue caſe. Then muſt you pray for youre genytoures / your progenytoures / &amp; parentes / that is to ſay / your fathers / your mothers ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytual and carnal: as your ghoſtly fathers / or ſpyrytuall ſouereynes: your god father / your godmothers. Your natural father and mother. Your grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dfathers and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmothers. your brethers and ſyſters / and all your kynne.</p>
            <p>In the thyrde pleace is the datyue caſe. There muſt you pray for benefactours / good doers / of whom you haue receyued any maner of
<pb facs="tcp:8861:5"/>gyfts ſpyrytuall or temporall vnto the welth of your ſoule and body. In the .iiii. place is the accuſatyue caſe / where you ſhulde praye for your enemyes / ſuch pſones as by any meanes haue noyed / hurt or greuyd you eyther ghoſtly or bodely: that is to ſaye / in your ſoule / or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners by any ſuggeſtyon / intyſynge / euyll cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeyle / or euyl example. In your fame / or good name / by detraccyon / back bytynge / or ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drynge / or yet by famylyer companye. For a perſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely is reputed / and ſuppoſed to be of ſuche condition as they ben with whom he hath conuerſacyon and company. And for them that haue hurt your body eyther by ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes / or by any other accaſyon / haue hyndred the ſtate / and helthe therof. And lyke wyſe of your worldly gooded / or poſſeſſyons. For all theſe maner of enemyes muſt you praye / that o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r lorde god wolde forgyue them as you do / and as you forgyuen wolde be / and that they may come to right charyte and peace. The .v. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is called the vocatyue: that is to ſaye the c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llyng caſe / wher you conuenye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly may cal / <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> / and praye vnto our lorde for all maner of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſones that ben out of the ſtate of grace / <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her by i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidelyte as turkes / Saraſens and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> other. Or els by errour as all maner of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heretykes / or elles by any deedly ſynne or
<pb facs="tcp:8861:5"/>offence to god. Pray foral theſe maner of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones that they maye come to the ryght waye of theyr ſaluacyon. In the .vi. and laſt place / is the ablatyue caſe. where you muſt praye for all them that be taken out of this lyfe / &amp; that dyed or paſſed the ſame lyfe in charyte / &amp; that now haue nede of prayer. In the whiche you may kepe a forme of the ſame ordre that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / that is to ſaye. In ſtede of the nominaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue where you prayed for your ſelfe: you maye now praye for all thoſe that do byde in payne for any defaute or offence done by your exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or occaſion. And for the genityue in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde place / for your parentes / and all your kynne departed this lyfe. And in the .iii. place / for the datyue: pray for your benefactours paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed. And for the accuſatyue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .iiii. place / you may pray for them that lyue in payne for any occaſyon / or any example that they gaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. And in the .v. place / for the vocatyue. Praye for all them that haue greateſt paynes in purgatory and leeſt helpe here by the ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of prayers. And for the ablatyue in the .vi. and laſt place. Praye you for all ſoules in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. And that you may be the more apte to pray / cal thre thynges oft tymes vnto remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce / that is to ſaye. what you haue ben / what you be / and what you ſhalbe. Fyrſt by Rotable leſ.
<pb facs="tcp:8861:6"/>reaſon of your body: you were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyued of the moſt fylthy abomynable mater of man / ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefull to be ſpoken / fetre more vyle then the ſluche / or ſlyme of the erthe / and after borne in a ſynfull ſoule / and purged onely by grace. And now (as vnto the body) you ben a muk<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hepe or donghyll / more vyle than any vpon erthe. yf you remembre what dothe yſſue day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; come forthe / out of the meates of your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. And your ſoule is dayly in ſome ſynne: or (at the leaſt) full lyke to be. what you ſhalbe as vnto youre body: you may ſe in experyece: wormes meate and erthe agayne. And what ſhall become of youre ſoule: no man in this world can aſſure you. To remembre than the loyes of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; paynes of hell &amp; that both ben inſimte endles / and without rebate / but bothe euer encreaſynge and neuer ſeaſynge / neuer haue eaſe nor reſt / but euer contynue and euer laſtyng. To remembre than: I ſay / theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges / may greatly moue you to haue your ſelfe in good a wayte / and ſtudye howe ye maye auoyde the one and obteyne the other. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brynge ſpectally how great a loſſe it is to loſe heuen / and howe vnconfortable gaynes to wynne hel / and how ſoone / and how lyghtly eyther of them may be goten or loſt. wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any thyng than of aduerſyte / hurte / or dyſpleaſure
<pb facs="tcp:8861:6"/>fortune / or fall vnto you: thynke than or yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn that yf you were in hell / you ſhulde haue the ſame dyſpleaſure and many worſe. And ſo to auoyde thoſe: you ſhal here (the better) ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fre / and for our lorde the more pacyently bere al theſe that now be preſent or may come here after. And in lyke maner / yf any good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperyte or / pleaſure happe or come vnto you: thynke then that yf you were in heuen / you ſhulde haue that pleaſure / and many more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentioyes. And ſo for the feruent deſyre of thoſe ioyes: you ſhall ſet lytell by any wordly conforte or pleaſure. A good contemplacyon therfore may it be vnto you in feeſtes of holy ſayntes (you may i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Englyſſhe Martyloge breuely ſe the lyues of many ſayntes for euery daye in the yere) to thynke and recorde howe great paynes they ſuffred here for the loue of out lorde / and how ſhorte theſe were / &amp; howe ſoone paſſed / and then agayne / how meruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous rewarde they had therfore in ioye &amp; blyſſe euerlaſtynge. So the troubles and tormentes of good perſones: ben ſoone / and ſhortly gone &amp; ended. And the ioyes and pleaſures of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſones done ſoone fade and fle for euer. The good pſones / for theyr troubles ſuffred here vpon erth: done get &amp; wynne eterne and euerlaſtyng glorye / whiche the euyll perſones
<pb facs="tcp:8861:7"/>done loſe. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary theſe euyll and ſynfull perſones / for theyr ioye and pleaſures here / done reygne by exchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge eterne &amp; euerlaſtyng ſhame / and rebuke with peyne / and wo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecable. whan ſo euer than you ben dyſpoſed to ſlugyſnes / or to be drowſy / remyſſe in pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er or dull in deuocyon: than take this lytell werke / or ſome other good treatye / and rede thetin / and euer note well the contentes ther of / and alſo what is ment therby. And yf you be not therby delyuered or eaſed therof / than ſhyfte vnto ſome other werke / or occupa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon / ſo that euer ye auoyde ydlenes / and all vayn paſtymes / which in dede ben loſetyme. And than remembre that thoſe that now by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in payne / eyther in hell / or yet in purgatory for ſuche tymes ſo paſſed or loſt / had leuer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the worlde / haue ſuch tyme to redeme theyr paynes by / as you maye haue yf you wyll. Tyme than vnto all perſones well occupyed is very precyous and dere. Beware well ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore: howe you ſpende it / or paſſe it. For you can neuer reuoke it / nor call it backe. yf the ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me paſſe you by trouble / and vexacyon / thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke they ben happy / and gracious that ben paſt thee wretched lyfe / and now i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blyſſe / for they ſhal neuer haue any ſuche myſery. And whan you fele a conforte or conſolacyon ſpyrytual / 
<pb facs="tcp:8861:7"/>thanke god therof / and thynke the dampned ſoules ſhall neuer haue any ſuche pleaſure. And thue let this be for your exercyſe in the datyue. At nyght whan you go to reſt / fyrſte make a counte with your ſelfe / and remembre how you haue ſpende / or paſſed that daye and tyme / that was gyuen you to be vſed in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue / and how that you haue beſtowed youre thoughtes / your wordes / and your werkes.</p>
            <p>And yf you fynde no great thynge amyſſe / gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the whole laude and prayſe vnto our forde god. And yf you perceyue contrary / that you haue myſſpended any parte therof / be ſory therfore / and beſeche our lorde of mercy &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyuenes / and promyſe and verely purpoſe to make amendes the nexte day. And yf you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue portunyte there vpon it / ſhalbe full conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyent for you to be confeſſed on the nexte mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe. And ſpecyally yf the mater done / ſayde or thought by delyberate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent / do greuouſly wey and worke with a grudge in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcyence: than wolde Iaduyſe you neuer to ete nor drynke / tyll you be dyſcharged therof / yf you maye conuenyently get a ghoſtly father. Now for a concluſyon of this werke / put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you / as by caſe or ymagynacyon .ii. large cytyes / one full of trouble / turmoyle / and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerye / and let that be hall. The other cyte full
<pb facs="tcp:8861:8"/>of ioye / gladnes / conforte / and pleaſure / and ſet that be heuen. Loke well on them both / for in both be many dwellers / &amp; great company. Then caſt and thynke within your ſelf what thige here myght ſo pleaſe you that you ſhuld chuſe the worſe cyte / or what thynge ſhulde duſpleaſe you on the other parte / wherby you ſhulde withdra we your ſelfe from that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue that myght counay and brynge you vnto the other cyte. And whan you haue ſtudyed well here vpon and can no thynge fynde / I dare well aſſure you yf you kepe well the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes and counſeyles of this lytel leſſon / you ſhall fynde the ryght waye / for the holy ghoſt wyl inſtructe and teche you where you be not ſuffycient of your ſelfe / ſo you endeuoyre and gyue dyfygence / to bere a way and to folowe that here is taught. Rede it euery weke ones or twyſe / or oftener yf you wyll. And where you profyte gyue thankes / laude / and prayſe vnto our lorde god / and moſt ſwete ſauyour Iheſu chryſt / who ſende you his mercy and grace / that alwaye lyueth god. In ſecula ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culorum. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>¶ Finis.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="translators_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:8861:8"/>
            <p>¶ This was brought vnto me in Englyſſhe of an olde tranſlacyon / rughe / and rude / and requyred to amende it. I thought leſſe labour to wryte newe the whole / and I haue done vnto the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce not very nere the letter / and in dyuers places added ſome thynges folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng vpon the ſame to make the mater more ſentencyoue / and full. I beſeche you take all vnto the beſt / and pray for the olde wretched brother of Syon Rycharde whytforde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8861:9"/>
            <p>¶ Imprynted by me Robert wyre / dwellyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge at the ſynge of ſeynt Iohan eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelyſt / in ſeynt Martyns paryſſhe in the felde beſyde Charynge croſſe in the byſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhop of Norwytche rentys.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Wyer (1529-60) with his name and mark, depicting St. John writing the Book of Revelation on the island of Patmos with an eagle on his right holding an inkhorn</figDesc>
                  <head>ROBERT <figure>
                        <figDesc>merchant's mark</figDesc>
                     </figure> WYER.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8861:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
